We all have an experience that we are free in our actions.
We choose what we say, we choose what we do.
We can choose to act on our impulses or choose not to live them out.
Despite this, many philosophers ask themselves, and have done so for a long time,
If we are really as free as we feel.
Many even mean that our experience of influence over our actions is a mental
post -construction of an act that was inevitable or even predetermined.
They thus mean that you could not do anything else at this moment but to look at this.
The problem is based on the fact that we live in a determinated world,
That is, a world where nature is caused.
An apple does not fall to the ground because it decided to leave the branch,
but because of a complex amount of causal effect.
Some of the variables that affect when the apple falls are;
the size and mass of the apple, the size and age of the tree,
the thickness of the branch, possible genetic defects, height above the ground, temperature, rainfall, winds,
Time of year, external influence in the form of animals, and so on ...
What finally causes an apple to fall at exactly a certain time is too complex for a human being
Be able to figure out - we can't possibly know all variables.
Despite this, most people agree that if we knew all the conditions
So we could figure out exactly when the apple would fall.
The fate of the apple is thus determined.
Sometimes in these discussions the term "predetermined" is used in these discussions,
Often thought as synonymous with determinated.
You may say that it is therefore predetermined when the apple will fall.
However, there is a point in not using this term as the term "predetermined" suggests that someone,
Often interpreted as God, in advance has decided when things will happen.
This is usually not what we mean, although there are of course theories
About all events takes place according to God's predetermined plan.
Nature is thus determined, it can theoretically predict if you can all parameters.
This also applies, for example, to physical or economic systems.
If you have knowledge of a projectile's exit speed, output direction, form, the strength of the wind,
Humidity, height above sea level, etc. can be determined exactly where it will land.
Why then would man differ from the basic conditions
That seems to apply to everything else in the universe?
Should we and our brain not obey the same causal effect as anything else,
After all, we are made up of the same matter?
Each time you make a decision on something,
So you make this decision based on past experiences and the current conditions.
Imagine now a hypothetical creature (in philosophy often called Laplace's demon) that has knowledge
About each particle and every event in the universe and has the ability to analyze all this.
In addition, the human brain is full of corresponding "routines and algorithms",
structured as a neural network in our brain.
That is why we can learn things and think.
An example of a "thinking" computer capable of making your own decisions is IBMS Watson,
an artificial intelligence that interprets natural language.
In 2011, Watson won the American version of Jeopardy!
against the human finalists.
Watson is not a regular computer but consists of 90 interconnected servers.
No one claims that Watson has any free will, but the performance illustrates the technological development well.
So do you mean that a computer will never be able to enjoy genuine free will
So you have a challenge in explaining how man can do it.
In a survey from the Max Planck Institute in Leipzig and Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience
In Berlin from 2008, 14 healthy subjects were examined with the help of a brain scanner.
Random letters were shown on a screen, a new letter every half -second.
The people had to press a button whenever they felt it during the trial.
So longer we have the experience of a free will, everything flows as usual in any case.
This is in itself absolutely true, but if there is no free will, this would get
Extreme consequences for, among other things, morality, for right and wrong.
Ethics and morals are about choosing the right or wrong.
Documents that violate our ethics vary from inappropriate (for example, downloading a
copyrighted file) to gross criminal (murder and rape).
Criminis then receives their penalty based on how much they violated our laws and regulations,
which in turn is based on our perception of ethics and morals (right and wrong).
But if our actions are determined, it means that a criminal could never have acted differently.
The person had as much impact on his action as the apple falling from the tree.
But how can one justify the person to be punished?
But we can also turn to the reasoning and claim that it is problematic to punish criminals,
Although they could not affect the crime themselves.
We can easily point out that the punishment in the same way as the crime is determined.
So we had never been able to choose not to punish them.
One problem with determinism is that you easily end up in an “you could not act differently,
I could not act differently ”discussion.
It is easy to point out that whatever is said, it is determined
And nothing else could ever have been said or imagined.
One answer to what enables our "exception" from the otherwise determinated world is that God has given us free will.